yeah
all right let's get started it's a short
one though
yeah I think okay let's get going okay
so uh recall well we and we're gonna end
it at that time uh I'll welcome to a
certainly uh let's pass in the group of
the following lagrangian uh still for a
mechanical system with one degree
freedom and the Branded uh want to have
uh Square minus one half two squares
G Q squared uh Q thoughts word
um now uh uh I come in last time that uh
you know this kind of a queue depends
again
all right now uh in fact as I uh at the
end of lecture notes uh uh which I
didn't write on the board uh last time
um in this case is Dr tossable to uh do
a redefinition of your generous
coordinates Q you're trying to compute
some other coordinate you can't absorb
this term into the into the standard
camera so you could do that
uh generally uh with more than one
coordinates uh it's not always possible
to absorb uh this kind of Q dependence
into the static electron without the Q
dependence in this with us for our time
um but I do not want to discuss in more
General case uh just to avoid uh having
to write more you know copyright format
on the board I'm just going to
illustrate the point with a simple
example even though in this example
I could have absorbed uh let's turn by
by definition if I do that every
definition you've got to check you can
absorb this understanding turn but then
I'm going to get a correction to this
potential term and the new coordinates
which looks just like the Animal
Hospital okay so um if you were to do
that at a classical level the classic
mechanics it's in quite this model quite
similar to it
the physical results uh to be that
different
um for the for the quantum theory uh but
we're gonna try to proceed and and uh
the quality Theory defined by the
pattern we're going to see what happens
um and uh once again to avoid some
complications with factors that I and
ordering operators and so that's we're
going to uh do the weak rotation and
work with the uh euclidean or the
lagrangea
um so this Q uh
um uh and uh I will write to euclidia
around you because minus L with this
stuff so I could do a challenge
Q squared uh and this variable is going
to have the same sign so a G Q square is
all right so
um so this will be the equilibrium what
we're going to be working with
uh and uh once again we're gonna expand
uh perturbatively in G
um uh say for the of durable that is the
two coin foreign
space language in terms of those two hat
operators and for now uh with this uh
with that that understanding I'm just
going to compute function around
uh and uh and the rule is uh uh is clear
just like last time uh the only
difference the last time I had the Q to
the board now I have a Q squared the
power Q squared so it has to change the
vertex a little bit but apart from that
the graphs the final graph that we're
gonna they're gonna contribute to this
two point coordinate function uh is uh
pretty much the same setup perhaps with
some additional decoration because you
have the crack of this so I'll tell uh
and which we'll do now all right so uh
so this will be given by so first of all
we still have the harmony propagator g0
now remember this was some functions one
half e to the minus two absolute value
but I'll just uh I won't plug that in
before the moments
um and then we still have graphs like
this
right we'll have a single vertex
okay so
um now uh uh well they're g once again
we still have a single graph like this
but let's look at whether this guy is
in terms of the actual uh formula
so
so this map
uh let's calculate
um so this way more questions
we got a few towel
um uh two zero well let me let me
provide a q zero and on the right hand
side just to match with it because there
is that one release it's not important
uh and we're expanding each of the minus
capture each other it's minus so there's
none of minus 10 there two minus signify
cancel okay
[Music]
Prime uh
squared
um so we have all of this inserted by
the way instructed this graph correspond
to remember there's a connected with
concussion okay so according to the
graph the pattern of contraction is that
this Q is going to be contracted with
one of the cues here this cubic time
with one and Q is here and another pair
of Cubes here I can cut it but
um but uh when I choose this graph like
last time all the four series two powder
identical right so we have some
commentatory factor four times three yes
you might recall
um now they're not quite all identical
some have derivatives some don't have
derivatives so I actually have to uh
uh count them separately okay so if I
just join this graph is nothing up here
so so
yeah yeah I have to uh do this a little
bit more carefully but but we can do
that so uh in order to do that we just
have to remember
um
that uh
in writing this vertex
uh each of the leg coming out of the
vertex represents one of these cubes uh
but two of them have a derivative on it
uh and I can choose which one whether
the one with the directive or without
you or to be contracted with either this
Q or that kid
all right so so I can represent the
derivative by uh let's say a little uh
um uh blue uh robotics little blue uh
over here
um and so for example
here so each one of these represents a
uh Prime uh
so that's one possibility uh and then of
course you can produce the others uh so
there's you can also put the blue the
derivative on these two lines or
uh again
two more possibilities
and so I can
do this
um I can
also for this
um well actually
right I also have I can also do this
um
but I think that's all the possible ways
to sprinkle the two derivatives uh on
these uh
okay
uh any questions so far
um all right so um
uh let's uh let's focus on the first one
we've got the first one is gonna uh
let's see it's gonna be the one that uh
looks a little bit problematic to the
others are more or less going to be
standard
um in fact for example uh if you think
about oh okay let me just write this out
so see more explicitly what you point
out
um so uh for this pattern of
construction this corresponds to the
situation where uh uh where um these
queues outside are contracted with the
queue here without directly and then we
used to get back with
so uh so this diagram is calculated by
the following weekly practice and Q
Power Q 0 and G over H integrals through
Tau just write this down two top running
u sound Prime and d q cell Prime d q r
Prime
uh and uh the pattern of contraction is
that so please do with the derivative I
can practice with that two
and then that's it so so this is the
only these are the only instructions
that correspond the graph of this uh of
this
any questions so far
okay so now let's let's plug in
calculator this is equal to uh G over
four times integral of e power Prime so
this gives us a factor of G the
probability power minus Tau Prime
uh
right uh these contractions give us a
factor of G zero of uh
is
a level of interactions
remember and of course the two zero was
actually a function of collapse of
values
uh but uh but
what what is this what is this
um so for that let's just do a little
calculation because this is totally
obvious but it's just uh you all you can
do is to separate those uh two times
let's say you consider two power one
which is
that right uh so what is this word
contraction
well this might be trying to do the same
as the variation of derivative of that
power one derivative we write the Tau
two of the contraction uh one two times
two these are the same thing okay
why are why there are the same thing by
definition okay
you should definitely derivative right
so derivative like a difference of two
power two with q52 plus Delta Tau two uh
but you know
uh two if I shift the argument here
that's just a different variable in the
functional integral and the way the
contraction is calculated is exactly by
the same propagated
all right so so uh so these are my
definition identity
okay so the result of this is just
detail one detail two of G that one L2
which is G and power minus times two
zero
uh and of course uh this is the same as
um
the same as minus 0 to the power one
by one minus R2
okay and uh and then I take the limit if
I take limit uh two going to Tau one so
that these two times the euclidean times
go inside like that I just got minus
zero
and that's the result
um any questions about this manipulation
here
this will be true for any kind of
working contraction here
where this yeah this is from uh uh you
know professional calculus right okay
okay yeah
any other questions there can you
explain again the first line where you
can fill up like the explanation uh
right so uh what is let's recall from
freshman calculus this is defined to be
a limit okay let me erase it will
understand that uh
two minus two l two over the other one
um now uh
right uh now
you know then I just calculate the
contraction of of this Cube and this Q
which is the other two separately
because these are different variables
yeah every time if I have a shift to the
argument out this is just another
variable all the q's house were
different measures how are are infants
are the variables in your functional
integral so they just contracted
independently of each other and then I
take the combination the result is the
same as taking the derivative of the
contraction
uh well uh all I'm doing
is that you compute this as a functional
too and then take a limit how to go into
Tau one
uh uh that's right this is the viewer so
I'm using the partial rotation but it's
just a single variable of course this
means that I take the derivative of this
function entice and set as argument to
zero but right that's the usual notation
okay so uh so that's our result here so
uh we're very welcome thanks I will
write down the answer minus partial
squared uh G zero of zero
um okay so but of course uh as we uh
have said before uh it's uh last night
and it's important convenient to write a
four-year representation of that
um and so let me do that right
everything in terms of is four year uh
um representation which is a bit
convenient because uh it's uh it's
directly tied to this uh picture with a
momentum flow so I'm going to pay going
in
here and uh over there and the
convenient thing about the point
reputation is that you can just
integrate out this power Prime variable
and all that does is that it implements
this conservation of the K that goes
into
there's Vertex or Edward vertex so so uh
so to repeat the same exercise a lot I
mean Prime uh from these first two
factors you're going to get into the ik
pal over
um K squared plus one uh squared so let
me just remind you that this Factor one
over K squared plus y squared come from
these two propagators in this four
years-based representation right last
night and this is how this comes along
with the right
um but then uh there's this additional
Factor here which I can write in
employee representation uh as integral
of DK Prime over to Pi
um so uh K Prime Square that's one that
would be the case uh it would just be
that if I didn't have this derivatives
that's what we had last time but now we
have the derivatives uh and if you go
and rewrite this in the representation
you find that the derivative just gives
you a factor of K Prime squared in the
numerator
I I mean you know
recall that uh yes
the point of repetition of that so take
two derivatives
on this you just get a backup minus K
squared but the minus signs of getting
that to get a backup K squared okay
Prime squared in this case uh and uh and
they start out to zero
whatever you call it
um all right so so that's the result of
an integration range is always reminds
me into Infinity by these days
uh any questions so far
okay now let's try to calculate let's
try to evaluate this while you have a
problem uh this is Divergence
um
this integrand goes to one in both
directions
well uh of course it was Divergent
because you should have complained
earlier this guy here is going to be
fine remember our two zero
of Tau
was one half e to the minus value you
can plot this function right
L to zero Tau uh it looks like this
so if you take the second majority of f
equals zero uh it's infinite
a little question that's what you see
from the polio repetition as well
uh okay so we encounter something bad
right so so this this thing is this
thing here is infinity
foreign
um numerically
um so uh so what is going on what what
is uh we have done something wrong okay
so what did we do that was wrong
right and yeah
proposal
I think everything will happen
this expression is identical to that
extent
okay so uh
so what was wrong
um well nothing that I wrote on the
board the calculation was completely
correct
um
uh so uh
but you know why is it that uh well you
know you had to think about the source
of Divergence it came from
doing this book contraction of this DQ
and how to do queue and go time
um and um a clear more clear way to
track down the source of the Divergence
is in avoid architecture so the boy
impatient I didn't write this explicit
on the board uh but we can track another
transformation of cube I wrote this in
the lecture note that was posted so you
could directly level in the Fourier
transforms for you right
um so you can write a few town to be uh
some uh okay
[Music]
there if you are too likely to grab it
yourself
um but um
uh the uh origin of this uh so from that
perspective
um the origin of this beverages is from
the integration at large values of K
Prime
uh and that has to do with the
contraction
uh the word contraction of this audio
mode of Q
um at large wave numbers
uh why do we have this contraction
equation of the larger wave numbers is
because in the path integral we have
this measure
uh and
uh this measure the way we actually
calculate in the Fourier space as you
have seen in the first problem set
um you can uh abdominalization this will
just be integral e to Theta k
over all wave number okay
but as you have seen it did in the first
problem said even with harmonica
oscillator sometimes
you only calculate uh this uh maybe
it'll be fine unless you regularize
after all mathematically this is uh this
kind of integration is not sensible
unless you in terms of independent or
integral by cutting off let's say the
wave numbers in this case actually a
wave numbers would be continuous but uh
you know the homework uh you saw an
example with numbers were discrete and
indeed you can first Realize by cutting
it at a large wave number and you
calculate the physical observable of
interest and homework in the partition
function and at the end at the end of
the day when you have responded quite
normalization you take the color of
infinity and that would sensible answer
so in this case uh you might uh want to
do the same thing because otherwise uh
you know there's no guarantee the path
of the goal was
um you know well defined in the first
place so uh so let's uh do we always
have to regularize
sometimes we get away with not
regularizing we're lucky but generally
you always have to regularize
um and uh so we can verbalize by say
cutting off
um there's
um weight number of 40 amount of view
that appears in the pathogable measure
some large number uh and only do this
um and then hope that at the end of the
day when you calculate some physical
variables of interest you might uh you
might end up with some quite as a result
but there's no guarantee of that at the
stage uh so but let's try
all right so if you do that if you
define the measure uh with this
organization then uh the effect of that
is every time you do the weight
contraction you're always going to
integrate in the momentum in the
frequency space you're only going to
integrate okay up to that
so of course if you do that uh that will
turn this integral uh into into a finite
integral
um okay so so if you regularize uh
if they regularize uh
with this
shut up
uh then uh you're just gonna
so here you're gonna integrate every
time how to learn
um and of course that's going to make
this finite but uh it's still going to
be a number that is for the lamba and
when land is large this number is so
large but uh but at least it's an
expression that's uh that's mathematical
sensible and we can try to proceed and
calculate physical observables of
interest uh by the way I should say that
uh uh now uh
we only have one of these diagrams but
you can you can verify for yourself I
wrote this introduction uh
that we posted
um but it's not hard to verify that uh
the same kind of diversion does not
occur in any of the other diagrams this
is the only diagram that has discovered
the other way I said uh you have to
divide by another cut off by then I
could get away with it so we haven't
Define this way and we can see what it
makes sense again
the original integral was over all the
pain
uh well we'll see yeah
okay
all right yes
in general will the actual time
um
uh uh well it's better not if your
theory is defined if you have fun behind
your system uh it better not matter at
the end but that's not guaranteed at the
state
but I'm having a population kind of
obvious it's about management
um all right so but let's proceed well
you also an example the homework that
you did get away with in that case we'll
see what we're going to get away in this
case it's not obvious
okay uh so uh let us for example let us
inspect the common sequence of this on
this uh two-point version I saw was
intimately applied to the energy
Spectrum of the model
the spectrum of having someone
and so for example we saw that last
night at this 2.4 later uh is what I
call this voltage G of how and this was
a really uh a metaphoria representation
uh Decay because
over a plus one minus this is okay on
the second one k remember this was
calculated by the countries diagram
[Music]
s everything is
um by the way uh this Sigma K and later
we'll see the quantity context this has
a uh
for it it's a very poorly uh cells and
terminology it's called self energy uh
in the current context uh this name
doesn't have any
is
um and um
we saw this last time so yeah
we calculated and we calculated leading
uh contribution to this right so um
uh what we saw was that uh this uh
signal okay as weather G
uh
uh receives the contribution
uh the contribution from this diagram
uh
well we please talk about another
several diagrams but the other diagrams
are finite those only one is the
Divergence so the Divergence would be
diverted contribution uh which is which
is this quantity here that is just that
just G over four uh
this Lambda over I
stand that number this is the Divergence
well this will be diverted if you remove
that we will cut off and that uh This
plus something finally
okay
uh no uh well at the end of the day we
do need to take that Infinity
um and this skill looks problematic
right because uh we said last time that
actually uh the the pose of this
integrand which is the zero of the
denominator
advantages as some complex actually
period imaginary K uh that this sequence
of posts on the upper half complex carry
plane we explained last time there are
some of the actual energy levels of our
model okay I'm telling you
uh so this will contribute
to the actual energy crisis with energy
levels or the first excitation energy
and if this diverges that uh looks bad
yes
you're gonna get uh
the land is large you can get something
that emergencies but like it's too
Lambda right this is
the rest will be fine
we're not going to worry about that but
most of you are concerned about the
Divergence because this thing to be uh
English inconsistency of our formula
okay so so uh so something is wrong
actually uh we end up with the basically
the answer doesn't make sense
okay so what did we do that was wrong
well uh this was actually the thing that
I wanted you at the beginning when I
discussed the derivation of the passing
for performance sketches
so
um I said that there can be ambiguity of
order H bar in this LeBron they try to
produce the correct exact connection
uh so so far we've said always said H
bar to one but it's useful to restore H
bar just to be able to keep track of the
uh the H bar dependence and uh and where
where the what are the functions versus
the classical contributions so the path
to the world when you play a signature
or sorry in this rotated version uh it's
a it's a I'm going to restore this H bar
um you find this here
um
well
uh do you believe the End come on Jim
um and uh
like that actually
um we know the the model is defined in
this way with us
uh lagrangian myself
um but there's a possibility that in
fact
um there could be a order H bar uh some
other H bar corrected to this uh after
all you know all we know April is that
this thing has to reduce the classical
LaGrange H5 to zero limit but who says I
cannot add some term of order is
zero this will still go away so I should
still go away
um
uh our goal is to
we want to have it I want this particle
to reproduce the physics of some
hamiltonian I want to fix the Hamilton
but you saw the hand intelligence is
also a potential ambiguity that's
wondering the p's and q's when you
contacts and these two are potentially
tied together by the relation the
precise relation is not obvious
um and let me find out another issue
which is also closing related which is
that uh uh you know I don't really know
that the measure is just exactly this of
a constant Factor what if the measure
has some acute dependence uh in fact if
you think about uh I made a guy in the
beginning that you could have made in
non-linear redefinition of variable
deals so they're going to turn this into
more standards around you which is two
thousand square credit cards we're going
to change the potential turn this into
something more like an harmonic acid but
if you do a non-linear here we
definitely some Q which of course you
are free to do in classical mechanics
the path in the world
you are going to introduce the Jacobi
the factor itself behind something
now you could imagine so let's say oh
but then we made a mistake
well actually you can even correct for
this mistake because the Jacobian Factor
get written as equal to something but
something is going to be some functional
of cube that could be written as an
integration compound because there's one
for each time
okay so this uh if you have a drink okay
Factor you could have imagined uh
Curriculum
by uh in second way that you restored it
correctly
well what would impactor look like uh
yeah
something in the exponents will have no
h bar dependence
so that was going to precise the quarter
H bar term
okay so what what H5 correction can
potentially account for the Jacobian
Factor right we would have missed if
that were the correct definition of the
model right so uh generally you don't
you just don't know if you start saying
that you know if you divide the model by
just saying that I'm going to quantize
this lagrangeas
happens your apron agnostic about you
know what are those possible recovery
factors right maybe you can take it to
do this but maybe that's not correct
definition of the model so you have to
figure out exactly what are these bar
Corrections
uh luckily in this example we have the
hamiltonian will provide them to assist
us to uh you know
it should be you can always try to do uh
the uh lagrangian to arrive at the
correct uh physics that matches with MSW
that's one way to proceed of course you
might say that we're going to defeat the
purpose in particle but so far we're
just trying to understand how the
formism works and
um
um I'm trying we can use the hamiltonian
as a guidance
um so uh and indeed uh okay so now uh if
we restore H bar where would H bar sit
in all these uh uh calculations of the
correlators
uh well uh in fact you'll find uh that
you find the a square
up there uh that just comes along with
the right
uh but then in the calculation of
um uh you see uh let's do uh
uh it's easy to see why you have H bar
up there because uh in the player space
you have a case k square plus one for
numerator and when you have like the
Gauss integral remember you invert the
coefficients that's the code the case
one plus one the numerator gets inverted
it's one over K bar plus one but this
one over H bar gets inverted into the
back of this box we have the H bar there
um and uh
uh and then
um
yeah if you calculate uh the diagrams
you can get the fact of H bar from this
property probability that is far from
here there's some H bar from here and uh
there's also a spar from this propagator
and then you've got one over H bar from
the vertex because you're just expanding
the
the financial purpose it comes back up
on the page bar
um and uh at the end of the day this
term compared to that term acquires one
attribute so it needs to cancel it
requires one extra packet
but but then remember we're summing up a
geometric series to get the expression
like this so in fact in the self-energy
this thing comes with the factor
of H1
so
anyway this is the idea to restore the
HR Factor you just remember where it
comes from
um but the point is that uh the question
now you can ask yourself is it where
April were agnostic about the possible
or the H bar correction so this
lagrangian is it possible that we choose
a specific term
here uh you have to cancel there's this
Divergence
um now and maybe you can do that uh so
um very important for instance
so the idea now is that we're going to
uh modify
to look around you
so uh we're going to Mommy bye
uh we're going there by adding
okay
time somebody's going to call the
counter term
context all it is
whenever I see the word counter term
what it means is that it's a term you're
supposed to include in the lagrangian of
the regularized
right the counter is nothing but a term
in the LeBron James uh but there's a
term that you uh may not have guessed
staring at the the classical expression
but in order to Divine the quantum
uh in the world uh with this
regularization uh you have to also
correspondingly modify the ground yet uh
by some kind of term the idea is going
to be that you know here you've got the
Lambda dependence the counter may also
depend on Lambda in such a way that the
other day he chose down him correctly
you take down to Infinity the physical
answer uh will have some kind of
well-defended
all right so uh let's see
um so the contract what would it be well
uh let's try it so uh so
um
let's try and development upon a term uh
now
um
order in G so far at order teaching the
first order it would have this
Divergence we want to cancel that
perhaps with some common term so let's
try it so some coefficient C we'll
figure out what it is times G
um and whatever it is this
bar for it to make sense so because it's
supposed to represent a Quantum
correction to lagrangian that will go
away in the classical element
um uh and uh let's just use let's just
sign this excuse whatever
so it's uh it's something proportional
to Q squared so this is like uh
correcting the frequency of the harmonic
oscillator itself if you wish
all right
um so uh
okay uh well it's very easy uh to
understand the effect of this uh because
all you are doing
this yeah you you can there's several
ways to do this you can either view this
as a Vertex with only two lights coming
out but we don't have to wire go through
all that exercise again because you know
this just this is a term that similar to
the term already appeared in the
original uh uh remember this was one
half
oscillator right so in the back of this
at least well the effect of this adding
this term is simply that you're gonna
replace this K square plus one it
replies to a square plus one plus uh
this solution H Bar C G
right so and that's that's very easy so
so we see that there's Sigma k
now what does this look like this looks
like
um well uh we're going to we're going to
get the correction and pull your H bar
um G
um
uh so uh
uh we saw right here that we have this
uh uh
last step over uh for pi
uh there's some uh finite stock uh this
one is that you can calculate this if
you want but I won't bother you know and
this part of the stuff is uh Hey
generally pay attention
uh I guess I raise the background now
but some of the other diagrams we are
finite I will give you additional okay
dependence but but uh but you know you
know I don't care about that too much at
the moment uh the the important Point
here is that if you uh
it's at this
um
uh well it's going to uh effectively
you're going to subtract from Sigma uh H
bar CG right so Sigma is a contribution
of this thing uh minus C
uh then that's it and uh and then higher
order terms of order G squared I wish or
not the duty at the moment
okay so so very simple so so the result
of having this kind of term is that
we're going to correct the self Sigma
self-energy but anyway shown having that
uh two-point function
um it's just another G is going to
correct this polar G term which is
really
an order H bar previously set the one
um but shifting this bypass
it's constantly being there the
professional content we're adding
um
uh so uh
uh the idea is now
we're going to uh choose
right so we're gonna choose
uh choose
if we choose C to be uh you know Lambda
over 4 pi plus some finite constant
and a constant
um well the C have to be constant by
definition uh but by our by our choice
so far that's how we're defining the
Strategic world when the fact you know
produces the right hamiltonian or not
that that's something we have to
investigate but I want to at least get
something that is that produces a
well-defined answer
you take a limit Lambda to Infinity uh
the result will be finite would be
finite uh but this is not very
satisfactory it doesn't seem very
satisfactory because uh
um
it's very arbitrary Finance number uh
right and you don't know a program where
the number is
at this level uh there is no way to know
what a number is because there's an
interest ambiguity how you define the
quantum here so to fix that finite parts
of the common term uh that's physics
that that's how you have to use some
other physical principle that with so
far uh do not know uh based on the
information of just this lagrangian
alone
okay uh if you have some additional
symmetry or something that might help
you in terms of accountable without that
uh there's uh we cannot pin down what
this model is
okay so uh that's the that's going to be
the status of this five people
now as I mentioned before uh this time
because you can have Metallica as well
when you try to contact the hamiltonian
and unless you without putting it down
what is the audio prescription there's
no way to sort of determine what this is
these things are tight one another
uh but in any case uh December right the
point here is that in order to Define
this happening world for this type of
lagrangea in this example
um we need to rationalize
we need to include the common term
uh this customer term might be Divergent
individually remove the cutoff so you're
supposed to Define
the particle by always regulating with a
cut off so the concept of dependent
cutoff and at the end of the day when
you do the conversation with the country
included uh you come to the physical
observables such as the sigma K or the
two-point query function and you take a
little Lambda capability at the end you
should restore a sentence that's the way
how you will Define uh the quantum
theory by happening
yes
so when we add this concept I can see
how you know we fixed this term in the
platform was no longer uh diversion in
the Islamic Infinity limit but don't we
mess up our lagration because now we're
LaGrange yes but the who carries were
like well actually it's not a technical
thing the physical things are uh you
know silver space I want to know whether
the spectrum of the states whether it's
very valuable the actual Department in
fact we'll see later that it could also
be the case okay so let me emphasize
that this important Point here
um so we want specifically Sigma K to be
to have fun and limit because it already
affects the actual values of energy
eigen values right so
um uh so you know it's thinking okay
they'll be fine then you don't have one
energy like a value so that would be
problematic it's now guaranteed that
this entire two-point function would
have people are defined because no
there's nothing sacred about the
operator Geo's path is going to be
defined for the package it could be that
uh the operator itself is still defined
but the difference from some work by an
operator by sometimes in the back
there's no reason why it has to be after
all you see these are all the H bar the
clouds are limited go away anyway
so there's nothing exactly about the
branch unless you have some critical
reason to believe that this term are
directly rate the physical observable
there's no reason why they have the same
finance and remove them regularly
uh and and also there's nothing sacred
about the operator cube right this
operative could have been receive an
infinite uh
the originalization but uh you know but
you know in the quantum theory the
quantum mechanics there always well
depend operators it may not be this
queue it may be
receiving that is also possible yes
um
uh yes of course if you change your head
like around you and you will generally
find a constant you'll change physical
Observer such energy levels so my point
is that you didn't know
is to begin with
at that order
this is
necessary yes
it's just kind of like oh I didn't say
there's a one-to-one correspondence I'm
just saying that it's a hint that
there'll be some ambiguity I'm not
saying that that's the only ambigued
uh any other questions
um okay so I said that uh you know in
this one mechanical system uh well
without additional principle some
additional symmetry whatever uh we
cannot really fix this in the final
Concepts uh after all in the usual
quantum mechanics uh if you're going to
propose hamiltonian functional use or
rather if you have a few heads uh you
know anything goes as long as it's a
conventional operator with the
foundation basic property like that and
if you can imagine any Quantum model you
want to get at any time you wanted to
have intelligence
um uh so in that context not much more
you can say about these common terms but
but a volunteer will turn out that
things are much more restricted uh
because I've read the visible account
and we'll see that uh in a large class
of field theories we're going to be
interested in uh in the squares and
very often this long terms are not
arbitrary and they are up to some small
amount of ambiguity they're more or less
all going to be fixed by the principle
of uh microcos Alex
okay so that's going to be uh the uh
well anyway that's that's where we're
going from
um and okay so uh I think with that we
are
finally done with uh this quality times
one and we're ready to actually do a
field Theory
um but let's summarize what we have
learned so far
um so with the Practical formulation so
we're learning we can do preservation
Theory with the family diagrams
um we've learned that you have to
regularize the past level you have to
add the contact
will be completely trivial in fact you
can probably already figure out the
roots to do from two even though I can
I've been quiet introduce your theory
yet but we'll do that properly uh next
lecture
um but uh
all you need to do is add some
additional variables special variables
uh and uh we'll see how that works uh
but before that uh just as a
um to prepare ourselves uh I should say
a few words at least about a classical
field Theory because I think uh perhaps
not everybody's uh coming to the stats
are uh familiar with uh
uh with a classical filter there's no
classical mechanics but actually a few
words about classical field here I think
in the uh old days uh you know students
will take a quite impossible skill
Theory but I think that that's standards
for this curriculum anymore so so I
should say a few words about uh
classical field Theory
um so
um
okay so um
uh
uh so all we need to do is to uh
consider classical mechanics but with
implemented degrees of freedom of a
specific type so so we're gonna replace
so so the classical
mechanics uh where we have this uh
generalized coordinates
uh we're going to replace this by uh
we're gonna replace this eye by some
continuous primary for instance they
could be some description X Vector like
so
lecture we're going to be interested
primarily in uh field theories that have
a random physics symmetry so later T and
X are going to be related by
uh from various symmetry learn
transformation
um uh and uh we can introduce asymmetry
in a way that's manifests at the level
of reaction
um so
um I want to emphasize that
um
uh here this x is a
uh it is going to be a label for the
coordinates the coordinates of this
mechanical system are the five
themselves
okay so at the instant of time
complexity uh you know the the the the
the dynamical variables are Pi where
this x is available you can use labeled
by the variables
um and uh as a matter of convention
um uh will be uh later always working in
uh indeed dimensional
we have CNN
uh you know space time
um where
they think of this x and the uh B minus
one
a dimensional Vector uh parameterizing a
special point and I'm always going to
write X mu to be uh
[Music]
ad summation of this Vector where this
x0 and the T are typically interchanges
sometimes I write x0 and to make learn
symmetry manifest sometimes if I want to
emphasize time Evolution I'll write a t
but unless otherwise say that this x
here and P are interchangeable
um
and so far I'm going at this point I'm
going to discuss uh Real Time with
Laurentian and Dynamics and the weak
rotation will play a role later when we
come to pattern
space
okay so uh and uh the classical
mechanics uh or the time evolution of
this field variable Supply will be
completely characterized by the action
so I didn't tell you what the action is
production with uh integral in time just
like in the ordinary mechanics but now
I'd have to also integrate in the
spatial coordinates of some laguology
intensity L
um that is the function of Phi of uh x
uh so so just be noted together as
Phi of x
if I have X without any label on it uh
it stands for this p-dimensional Vector
it's a 5x and have a partial mu Pi of x
um and of course uh if you adjust those
special integral this is what we usually
call that lagrangian is possible
mechanics but now this involved in
variables
um I should say that uh from the point
of view of lagrangea mechanics with
implemented degree of freedom and this
kind of thing this is not quite the most
General thinking right right there's
already some kind of a locality that
there's lagrangia this has some kind of
integral in this special coordinates of
a sound expression typically involve
only finding finally many derivatives
but at the same point
okay see this is already a bit
non-trivial there's nothing
that's built in um but if you want to
write a manifestive Lorent invariant
action uh is uh these are the most
General the most obvious part of action
to write down and we'll see that they
will indeed the right potential for
field theories okay
okay so uh
uh any questions so far
um now of course the equation of motion
In classical mechanics is still the uh a
variational principle that is the
variation of action we're back to
arbitrary the first father uh
zero and this function derivative
and uh so you know as usual if you
assume that the lagrangea is that only
depends the one that's the only
difference another person directed then
we can write the variation uh before
very
the first order the variable
so we can write the version of action
that's integral
in space-time uh well there's the
variation of Pi of x uh L by y of x
R and there's so many people are I mean
we usually like our red if you are
familiar with the rule of functional
variation
right
um
um now
uh the variation of the derivative of Pi
of X is uh by definition assignment
derivative of the variation of violence
um I hope this point is clear because
all I'm doing is that I start with the
pi of x i vary into a new five Max I
recall this Pi Prime of X I take uh you
know if I if I compare the derivative
before an after the variation the same
as the derivative of the variations it's
because linear personal advantage
turn the second term into something
proportional something to worry about
Parts assuming that that is uh Fields
playoffs are through passive Infinity
um
um and turn this into or maybe more
fantastic assuming that it's my
variation uh that is in fact Infinity uh
then
um
this
is
the motion to says that let's take up to
zero that would be the equation for
arbitrary of X that comparative action e
to the zero
um so so this is that this is also the
formula the ground equation for the
okay
um so let's uh look at uh the most
basic example
of this so we can take the uh
uh so the simplest example uh would be
uh three
uh scale the field
scalar yield right so we can take the
let's try to write down uh some uh
lorettes a variant expression uh so we
need a kinetic term
uh the character should look like uh d0
quite hot squared
plus five Factor one half just for
normalization
uh it should look like that no but we
want to make a lorency variant
um so this integration measure here is
valency variance as you might know
um
launching variant because the the large
formation Matrix this Lambda has
um
and uh so it's a Memory loans in very so
we just need to need this uh the Divine
identity to be a Lowrance uh covarian
expression uh and uh for that we have to
contract with indices uh in in a way
that man impersonates and the the way
the obvious way to do that is to replace
this
one uh
I mean you have seen this in homework
already and I'm always going to be using
a convention where this Matrix is that
of the mostly positive signature
before I mentioned like this
um so this has that genetic term of the
correct side
um and uh and then I can add some
potential term
uh the simplest uh
[Music]
I squared
okay so so that's the uh simplest uh
sort of non-trivial uh
density you can write down for a
relativistic invariance classical
filtering
any questions about this
um
so uh what is the equation of motion if
you follow the rule of the LaGrange
equation right the equation is important
um
uh you just very this we're about to buy
first uh you get so so the derivative of
L with back to Pi of x l at x with 25 of
X is that uh n minus M squared by
uh and the derivative of this with back
to partial meal of five is equal to
minus uh partial upper middle by
um and uh and so uh the equation motion
says that
um minus
R2 mu of Pi minus M Square five zero in
other words there's also usually write
this as the Box y minus n Square uh
okay
uh any questions so far
okay so let's solve the equation uh all
linear differential equations are
trivial to solve using uh
and uh so we can just write down all the
solutions
um
so uh the most General solution
the most General solution what do they
look like well uh
uh let's start with the foyer
transformed expression and let's write
this as integral
and V dimensional
let's say momentum variable just
momentum you just puts the name with
this variable doesn't mean anything just
some parameter okay new
integration okay
e to the i a valuations
uh at this point
um I'm always in the kind of a working
the Laurentian signature
um so this K is going to be some viewed
as a b dimensional Vector uh and
implicitly every time I write dot this K
dot of x
if this can actually viewed as records
in because I'm I'm always going to
Define this to be okay then I would
expect here my minus K zero with zero
the same as Theta lower mu Nu okay upper
mu X number I mean this is just a
connection
um to uh this will be convenient uh
working in the learning signature later
by to perform quick rotation I'm working
UCL signature the start will be replaced
by Euclid it in a product but right now
it's the Lawrence
this is just a definition okay I'm
allowed to always change the sign here
but we Define the variable anyway this
is the way I divide uh the convention
for the employer transform in the in
calcium space
all right and any question about this
there's nothing but the employee
Transformer back to each variable
independently but I can package it in
this way
uh okay so uh did you write this uh
what's the what's the solution to the
equation
yes
um
it's kind of like you know it's like
fine it's like and it's like I'm really
important
um
well uh you know if this will be you
would think that General you can yeah
like this the question should be a
constraint on app okay 40 seconds right
um
that's right so you think that you just
basic question right so you take this
and knock on that you get K square plus
N squared uh times uh F okay
uh I'll go zero
and that's the question all right uh
while you're gonna say that maybe this
doesn't have a solution if we're doing
okay but uh but there's a cash advances
that actually it was F okay
um where the biolence of interest in
this context applications distribution
so uh the segment of that
um so F of K F okay
okay is a distribution
to my other functions uh but it's
important support the meaning that
participating including that zero but
it's on the functions I can't really say
this value we're supported as uh kmu uh
beta can spread
this this constraint what you usually
called the mass shell
so it has to be something that roughly
speaking proportions of Delta function
in this time right
uh as long as so of course this
condition if you write it out this is
usually dispersion relation all right so
so that's just my understanding or
elsewhere plus okay squared plus N
squared equals zero uh so okay zero this
uh frequency the nine initially the
frequency uh the k0 is uh plus or minus
square roots of K letters squared plus
Cent squared and that's of course we
recognize uh uh would be the
relativistic dispersion relation uh for
a particle of mass m even though right
now I haven't said anything about
particle or mass and there's some
parameter that shows up in the LaGrange
density for this field very
um but anyway uh if you have a for any
distribution that's supported at the
mass shell this will be a solution
okay so this almost uh solves the
problem of time Evolution uh in this
very simple example but regulatory it's
very scalar yeah
um speaking uh this is not part uh
doesn't quite address the question of
time Evolution because the question
about time Evolution uh is uh really
about as we if I start with some real
configuration
zero what does it involve it
uh okay so that kind of answered through
this but I haven't quite answered that
question but we can do that
we can do that in the following way
so
um
so to fully solve this classical field
Theory uh we should address or solve the
initial value problem
um
that is to say uh so given
so what is the initial value problem
uh we need to capture the classical
state of the system and sometimes I
think of zero uh what are the parameters
we have to specify well in the cosmic
mechanic we have this no query that so
same thing here you have to specify a
fine by that
so to especially digital value problem
uh it's like saying given by at uh let's
say Time Zero but arbitrary spatial
position but that's not enough you don't
have to specify the time derivative uh
say B by DT of Pi times equals zero and
then so now I expect to my Q language
and that really is about to specify the
classical state of the system and they
want to determine it
positive p
so so that's the initial value problem
right that's what we care about In
classical mechanics
uh so how do we solve that uh well let's
just do the we'll have learned that this
is the most General solution and so so
let's expand
pi and table zero
using the general form of f of K let's
see what it looks like this looks like V
is okay so what we know is that uh
uh well the general solution
the genomics looking Pi of X we said
that it has to be uh supported uh on the
master
uh so uh that is Jose uh k0 and we're
I'm only here right k0 is determined by
K special Vector ocular PSI so the only
once you specify okay space a vector
there's only two choices okay for K zero
so we can say that Pi of X is uh
um integral in the Special K Vector uh
with some other function let's call the
top tilde of a special Vector
um e to the i k the three to Vector with
X rated Vector uh minus I uh so I'm
going to Define this Omega K so that
there would be square root of the base
where the second square plus N squared
that with a positive side to Omega K is
always positive
uh so I Omega k
X zero
so that's a one composite Solutions but
that's not all there's also some other
uh
uh minus E to that minus I well I could
have written plus here let me finish
writing and then explain this expression
so what I said earlier was um
right but I said earlier what about uh
the most General solution is of this
form uh that is uh K zero can be either
plus Omega K or minus Omega k
uh but now I also uh assume I guess I
didn't say this but biobex is a real
valued variable right x uh so for this
thing to be uh real valued I need these
two terms uh to be the complex conjugate
one another and three to always redefine
this okay so we prevented the minus
itself
minus itself
relax but then I know that this has had
to be the 100 than that
why do you know that
um
this this is the arbitrary there I I'm
always ready to redefine it I didn't say
this I didn't say that okay
it's just some parameter
so One Direction this way these two are
related back on this contribution so so
these are the most General Solutions I
can write in this way for some are now
really arbitrary function uh
Hey special Vector
um so now the initial value problem
uh
uh means that I want to specify Pi at
times zero and this time derivative by
time
right so so what are these uh the first
guy is integral uh the case special
Vector e to the I okay special Vector
topic with X ratio Vector of what uh
well I think I said x0 to zero and I
have this uh and so here I just have a
filter okay
back to there and plus F Delta star of
minus Theta
uh similarly if I take the time
derivative and then set due to zero
I just have uh
this
uh if I take a Time derivative
I uh yeah a factor of minus I Omega k
and then I have episode
minus until the star minus scalar
so uh now you see if I'm given these
initial values uh that specifies by
apply a transform uh both the plus and
minus mean a combination of f till then
until the star and therefore of course
the specified equivalent to the star
separately and once that is specified by
X is 25 and therefore the initial value
problem is solved at arbitrary time
uh any questions about this
uh okay so with that we have completely
settle the question of the classical
View at the time we also know this build
Theory and the writing to set the
quantum version of the theory uh we are
of course uh out of time
um let me just make a few comments
before uh getting to the quantum's
version here now this is the a very
simple uh free scalar Capital Theory uh
it's pretty in a sense that the question
of motion is reading and then there's a
look into things about the problem is we
almost finished as you can see here it's
easy to resettled by the boyfriend
um uh you could of course but yeah
classical filter isn't all that trivial
uh you know you can consider you know
non-linear propagation of waves there
could be some interaction uh term we can
add like by q five to Fourth and so on
and so forth when you have non-linear
terms
um you know the things don't just
populate according to this uh this kind
of uh simple
um dispersion relation uh and
furthermore you can have things like
solid pounds yeah you can have foreign
[Music]
we're not going to explore much of that
at the moment uh we're going to move on
to the quantum version of theory and
we'll proceed uh by two different
approaches of quantization I actually
person I should make a comment you know
we want to be vanished not every quantum
mechanical system of Interest come from
a stripper organization classes
for example uh you know particles with
the spin is not obvious how to get that
from a project system so a classical
business
uh go Theory but perhaps the most well
known example be that the permiance but
they're much more specific examples as
well uh but uh for now we're gonna be
studying the most straightforward most
simple kind of failed theory that can be
uh more or less understood by quantizing
a possible filter and we're going to
proceed uh by uh simultaneously with two
different methods of connotation one is
going to be phenomicalization which is
an operator and Builder space the other
with the pattern
they both have different they both have
pros and cons
Hamilton
system but as I mentioned before uh
lorative variants become manifest and
causality is not manifest the lagrant
information allows you to purely to
manifest the right variants uh but you
have the regulates and uh and that's not
always always and we will see how to
proceed with that standard
foreign
you know